

Université de Rennes 1, 263 av. du Général Leclerc, 35042 Rennes, France ■ valente.ramirez@univ-rennes1.fr | * valentermz.github.io/

 \mathbf{R}^{G} Valente_Ramirez | \square valentermz | \square 0000-0002-4594-430X | \square valentermz

Summary _

Researcher in mathematics working in complex analytic and algebraic geometry. My research focuses on the study of holomorphic foliations, vector fields and self-maps on complex manifolds. Interested in computational research, mathematics education, programing and data science. Experienced combining analytic and computational methods to solve research problems and communicating complex ideas to a diverse audience.

Employment _____

Institut de Recherche Mathématique de Rennes (IRMAR)

Rennes, France

LEBESGUE POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW

October 2017 - PRESENT

Education _

Cornell University Ithaca NY, United States

Ph.D. IN MATHEMATICS 2012 - 2017

- Thesis: "Quadratic vector fields on the complex plane: rigidity and analytic invariants"
- Advisor: Yulij Sergeevich Ilyashenko

Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México (UNAM)

Mexico City, Mexico

2007 - 2011

B.Sc. in Mathematics (Hons.)

- Thesis: "Strong topological invariance of the monodromy group at infinity for quadratic vector fields"
- Advisor: Laura Ortiz-Bobadilla

University of California Berkeley

Berkeley CA, United States

INTERNATIONAL EXCHANGE STUDENT

Fall 2009

Publications

- [1] V. Ramírez. "Strong topological invariance of the monodromy group at infinity for quadratic vector fields". J. Singul. 9 (2014), 193-202. DOI: 10.5427/jsing.2014.9n.
- [2] V. Ramírez. "An example of a non-algebraizable singularity of a holomorphic foliation". Enseign. Math. 62 (2016), no. 1/2, 7–14. DOI: 10.4171/LEM/62-1/2-3.
- [3] V. Ramírez. "The utmost rigidity property for quadratic foliations on \mathbb{P}^2 with an invariant line". Bol. Soc. Mat. Mex. 23 (2017), no. 2, 759-813. DOI: 10.1007/s40590-016-0127-5.
- [4] V. Ramírez. "The Woods Hole trace formula and indices for vector fields and foliations on \mathbb{C}^2 " (unpublished notes). Available at: arXiv: 1608.05321v1 (2016).
- [5] V. Ramírez. "Twin vector fields and independence of spectra for quadratic vector fields". J. Dynam. Control Syst. 23 (2017), no. 3, 623-633. DOI: 10.1007/s10883-016-9344-5.
- [6] Yu. Kudryashov and V. Ramírez. "Spectra of quadratic vector fields on \mathbb{C}^2 : The missing relation" (submitted). Preprint: arXiv: 1705.06340v2 (2018).
- [7] A. Guillot and V. Ramírez. "On the multipliers at fixed points of self-maps of the projective plane" (submitted). Preprint: arXiv: 1902.04433v2 (2019).

Programming Skills _____

Languages Python, Bash, R, LaTeX, Julia Systems and tools Unix, Git, SageMath, Jupyter

Talks and Presentations _____

RESEARCH PRESENTATIONS IN CONFERENCES AND SCHOOLS

ENCUENTRO DE FOLIACIONES Y SINGULARIDADES · Aug. 2018	Mexico City, Mexico
Geometry of Singularities and Differential Equations (poster) · Jun. 2017	Santander, Spain
HOLOMORPHIC FOLIATIONS IN ALSACE (POSTER) · Oct. 2017	Strasbourg, France
IV ENCUENTRO CONJUNTO RSME-SMM · Jun. 2017	Valladolid, Spain
CIMPA School on Singularity Theory in Topology, Geometry and Foliations \cdot Nov. 2014	Cuernavaca, Mexico
Attractors, Foliations and Limit Cycles (poster) · Jan. 2014	Moscow, Russia
Dynamical Systems Summer School · Jun. 2013	Dubná, Russia
46TH SPRING TOPOLOGY AND DYNAMICS CONFERENCE • Mar. 2012	Mexico City, Mexico
XLIV Congreso Nacional de la SMM · Oct. 2011	San Luis Potosí, Mexico
ALGEBRAIC METHODS IN GEOMETRY: COMMUTATIVE AND HOMOLOGICAL ALGEBRA	Guanajuato, Mexico
in Foliations and Singularities (poster) · Sep. 2011	

RESEARCH PRESENTATIONS IN COLLOQUIA AND SEMINARS

Mathematics Colloquium, Bernoulli Institute • Feb. 2019	Groningen, The Netherlands
SÉMINAIRE ANALYSE, IRMA · May 2018	Strasbourg, France
Séminaire de Systèmes dynamiques, IMT · Apr. 2018	Toulouse, France
SÉMINAIRE DE SYSTÈMES DYNAMIQUES ET GÉOMÉTRIE, LAREMA · Jan. 2018	Angers, France
SÉMINAIRE DE GÉOMÉTRIE ANALYTIQUE, IRMAR · Oct. 2017	Rennes, France
Dynamical Systems Seminar, Cornell University · May 2017	Ithaca NY, USA
Dynamical Systems Seminar, Institute for Mathematical Sciences · Apr. 2017	Stony Brook, USA
Dynamical Systems Seminar, Cornell University · Nov. 2016	Ithaca NY, USA
Dynamical Systems Seminar, Cornell University · Sep. 2014	Ithaca NY, USA
SÉMINAIRE DE GÉOMÉTRIE ANALYTIQUE, IRMAR · Jun. 2014	Rennes, France
Dynamical Systems Seminar, Cornell University · Feb. 2014	Ithaca NY, USA
Dynamical Systems Seminar, Cornell University · Dec. 2012	Ithaca NY, USA
Seminario de Singularidades y Foliaciones, Instituto de Matemáticas UNAM · Mar. 2011	Mexico City, Mexico

Fellowships & Awards _____

FELLOWSHIPS AND GRANTS

2017 – 2019	PRESTIGE co-Financing Grant Award · Campus France and the European Union
2013 – 2017	Conacyt Fellow (Becario en el Extranjero) · Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología
2015 – 2017	Graduate School Fellow · Cornell University Graduate School
2013 – 2015	Beca Complemento SEP · DGRI Secretaría de Educación Pública
2012 – 2013	Cornell Sage Fellowship · Department of Mathematics Cornell University
2011	Beca SIBES de Titulación · Secretaría de Educación Pública
2010 – 2011	Beca Conacyt de Tesista · Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología
2007 – 2011	Fundación Telmex Fellow · Programa Educativo Fundación Telmex

AWARDS AND DISTINCTIONS

2014	Eleanor York Award • For academic achievement and promise • Department of Mathematics, Cornell University
2013	Gabino Barreda Medal · To the top student in the class of 2007–2011 · Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México
2012	Sotero Prieto Medal · To the best undergraduate thesis in mathematics · Sociedad Matemática Mexicana
2010	Beca de Excelencia Académica · Prize awarded for academic merit · Secretaría de Educación Pública
2009	Beca de Excelencia Académica · Prize awarded for academic merit · Secretaría de Educación Pública
2008	Beca de Excelencia Académica · Prize awarded for academic merit · Secretaría de Educación Pública
2006	State Youth Award · Awarded for academic achievement · State Government of San Luis Potosí

Teaching Experience

Cayuga Correctional Facility

Moravia NY, United States

Aug. 2016 - Dec.2016

INSTRUCTOR

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Fall 2016 Mathematical Explorations

Department of Mathematics, Cornell University

Ithaca NY, United States

Aug. 2013 - May 2016

Spring 2016 Totally Awesome Mathematics Fall 2014 Multivariable Calculus for Engineers

Fall 2013 Differential Equations and Dynamical Systems

Facultad de Ciencias, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México

Mexico City, Mexico

TEACHING ASSISTANT Spring 2012 Ordinary Differential Equations III

Fall 2011 Ordinary Differential Equations II

Spring 2011 Real Analysis II Real Analysis I Fall 2010

Differential Topology I Fall 2010

Aug. 2010 - May 2012

Outreach and Volunteer Work

Cornell Prison Education Program

Ithaca NY, United States

Aug. 2015 - May 2017

INSTRUCTOR, TUTOR AND CONSULTOR

- Instructor for the course MATH 1300 "Mathematical Explorations" \cdot Cayuga Correctional Facility \cdot Fall 2016.
- Tutor for the MATH 102 "Introduction to Algebra" course \cdot Auburn Correctional Facility \cdot Fall 2015.
- Member of the Mathematics Committee for the Pedagogy in Prison program.

Department of Mathematics, Cornell University

Ithaca NY, United States

ORGANIZATION AND RESPONSABILITIES

2014 – 2017 Graduate program class representative 2014 – 2017 Organizer of the Dynamical Systems Seminar Spring 2013 Co-organizer of the What Is Seminar Co-organizer of the Olivetti Club Seminar Fall 2012

Languages .

Spanish Native English Bilingual

French Intermediate (B2 level) **Dutch** Beginner (A1 level)